<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="andrasnovoszath.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="andrasnovoszath.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-09-17T05:54:12-05:00</updated><id>andrasnovoszath.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Value this</title><subtitle>This is not another blog about bitcoin.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Finance Zero Sum</title><link href="andrasnovoszath.com/finance/zero-sum/valuation/2020/09/17/finance-zero-sum.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Finance Zero Sum" /><published>2020-09-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-09-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>andrasnovoszath.com/finance/zero-sum/valuation/2020/09/17/finance-zero-sum</id><content type="html" xml:base="andrasnovoszath.com/finance/zero-sum/valuation/2020/09/17/finance-zero-sum.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;is-finance-a-zero-sum-activity&quot;&gt;Is finance a zero-sum activity?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently thought about finance and whether it is a purely zero-sum game or has some value-add to it. I would like to know this to see if it is worthy of support either as a personal wealth source or as a social institution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not have time to read academic papers, so I simply did a google search (1-2 hours) and reviewed the top results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-i-found&quot;&gt;What I found&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just based on this short research, I barely found any substantial arguments against the zero-sum claim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What counterarguments I found were acknowledged that some forms,  like forex or short-term trading, are zero-sum.  They argued that, compared to the former types, ‘real’ stock trading can bring about benefits for both parties. Most of these were conflating terminology and concepts (like ‘luck’, or ‘value growth’).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are probably more substantial arguments in academic literature. Also, probably, there is the additional question of the social usefulness of financial markets for overall capital allocation, but that’s a separate thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-i-see-it-now&quot;&gt;How I see it now&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, as I started to dive into the topic, I quickly realized that is is a bit more complex than I thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s break up the question to the following cases:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;pure commercial relationship
trading of goods
finance&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pure-commercial-transaction&quot;&gt;Pure commercial transaction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When two people get into a commercial relationship, one is a ‘seller’, and the other is a ‘buyer’. Regarding the price, they have opposite aims. One’s income is another’s cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in this sense, every commercial transaction is zero-sum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;trade-of-comparatively-advantageous-goods&quot;&gt;Trade of ‘comparatively advantageous’ goods&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the seller gives away something they cannot use, but the buyer can, the exchange might benefit both. There is still the issue of the price for which they exchange the good, but the buyer’s benefit &lt;em&gt;from possessing the good&lt;/em&gt; might surpass its price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, here we can imagine a non-zero-sum relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;finance&quot;&gt;Finance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the people who trade and invest mostly want to get the most payoff for their buck. So this primarily seems zero-sum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mutual benefit might come about when their relationship to their asset is more complex than just trying to get the highest price difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I can see that I could think and write about this topic for a long time. Some ideas&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do we measure and compare ‘comparatively advantages’?
What are examples of not purely ‘buy low, sell high’ uses of finance?
How to measure the utility ‘ratio’ between price gain/loss and usability of the result of a buy event?
Is the social benefit of efficient capital distribution via financial markets a fluke, or has empirical evidence behind it?
Can we replace financial markets with an AI and delegate human creativity to more productive things?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Is finance a zero-sum activity?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The specific you</title><link href="andrasnovoszath.com/self-knowledge/specialization/2020/09/16/specific-you.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The specific you" /><published>2020-09-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-09-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>andrasnovoszath.com/self-knowledge/specialization/2020/09/16/specific-you</id><content type="html" xml:base="andrasnovoszath.com/self-knowledge/specialization/2020/09/16/specific-you.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-specific-you&quot;&gt;The specific you&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you are thinking about what business area to pursue, it is useful to focus on your specific situation and circumstance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-is-it-useful-to-find-a-specialization&quot;&gt;Why is it useful to find a specialization?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you do not look at your own specificities, you basically do not use knowledge and skills that others could use but cannot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have your history, your dis/abilities, your interests, and your own conceptual framing. Most of it might be useless, especially regarding all the people in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there are a few problems which maybe you are the only one who can solve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not about ‘finding your passion’ but rather to find out your skills, knowledge, approach, etc. These are actually quite tangible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-know-your-specificities&quot;&gt;How to know your specificities?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To see yourself better, write down your characteristics in as many dimensions as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some dimensions which you can look for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Knowledge,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Skills,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Experience,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interest.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing you can do is to create a spreadsheet and write as many of these things as possible. Then, value them on a scale (e.g., 1-5) showing how specific these traits and dimensions are to you, especially compared to others.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The specific you</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Valuation technology experimentation</title><link href="andrasnovoszath.com/technology/valuation/experimentation/2020/09/15/technnology_valuation_experimentation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Valuation technology experimentation" /><published>2020-09-15T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-09-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>andrasnovoszath.com/technology/valuation/experimentation/2020/09/15/technnology_valuation_experimentation</id><content type="html" xml:base="andrasnovoszath.com/technology/valuation/experimentation/2020/09/15/technnology_valuation_experimentation.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;valuation-technology-experimentation&quot;&gt;Valuation technology experimentation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might be useful and promising to experiment with technologies of valuation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-does-valuation-happen-now-and-how-does-technology-play-a-role-in-it&quot;&gt;How does valuation happen now, and how does technology play a role in it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Current technologies of valuation are in place because of different reasons. However, implementers rarely take into account the way the given technology plays a role in valuing things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;examples-of-the-use-of-technology-in-valuation-and-some-trends&quot;&gt;Examples of the use of technology in valuation and some trends&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Money is arguably the most prominent example. Probably this is not independent of that most of us still do not really understand all its effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other examples are in accountancy, trade, work management, economic metrics, environmental management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An obvious note is that, of course, other, not strictly technological components, like language, moral values, physical factors, etc., also have critial roles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;think-about-and-experiment-with-different-technologies-to-generate-new-valuation-situations&quot;&gt;Think about and experiment with different technologies to generate new valuation situations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accordingly, it might be beneficial to try out technologies with explicit valuation functions in mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the most part, and especially in early stages, this is concept-driven (i.e., we are looking for a particular effect to emerge). However, an uncertain but promising benefit would be discovering ‘unthought’ features due to things’ specific and idiosyncratic character.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-process-of-valuation-technology-experiments-and-its-main-challenges&quot;&gt;The process of valuation technology experiments and its main challenges&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the time, we cannot implement large scale infrastructures for the sake of experimentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, we can try other paths:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Implementation of a small-scale but very focused version&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scenario building&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Simulation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Game development&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The empirical analysis of similar processes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The empirical analysis of current technologies’ edge cases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Speculation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Incremental implementation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;current-action-possibilities-and-possible-future-directions&quot;&gt;Current action possibilities and possible future directions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As, currently, I this all is very high level and conceptual, and I am also mostly interested in discovery activities:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Collecting ideas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conceptual exploration of background ideas&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Case study analysis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Code experimentations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the future, I might be able to focus it down and branch out toward more serious development work.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Valuation technology experimentation</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Note-taking obsessions</title><link href="andrasnovoszath.com/note-taking/2020/09/14/note-taking-obsessions.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Note-taking obsessions" /><published>2020-09-14T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-09-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>andrasnovoszath.com/note-taking/2020/09/14/note-taking-obsessions</id><content type="html" xml:base="andrasnovoszath.com/note-taking/2020/09/14/note-taking-obsessions.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;note-taking-obsessions&quot;&gt;Note-taking obsessions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have an obsession with the process of note-taking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I often write down my ideas in the form of notes or tasks. I do this through multiple channels. Then I spend a considerable amount of time organizing them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One common frustration with organizing notes is that I can do this only along one hierarchical dimension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps one reason I like to code is that you can implement hierarchies along multiple dimensions more easily, although not always.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the single hierarchy, some notes tend to become forgotten as I put them in some deep end part of a category branch. This then requires me to constantly re- and review my notes and to recategorize and reorganize them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have looked into multiple note-taking software, but there is not really a perfect solution for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I found helpful is to require only a single function from a particular tool. So, for instance, I would use one particular tool or process for note-taking, then another for categorization, and perhaps a further one for review or note management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, however, needs that the different tools speak to each other relatively well. Ready-made solutions often do not allow it, so I found myself moving toward text-based tools. However, you need to utilize some basic scripting to make them work.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Note-taking obsessions I have an obsession with the process of note-taking.</summary></entry></feed>